# M. Tariq Aziz

# Data Scientist/Jr ML Engineer

Spring, TX ta.aziz221@gmail.com ttariqaziz.github.io in mtariqaziz ttariqaziz

#### **SUMMARY**

Certified Data Science professional with six years of experience orchestrating comprehensive data science workflows. Proficient in handling large datasets using various statistical tools, visualization methodologies, software development, testing, predictive modeling, and technical documentation. Enthusiastic and inquisitive individual dedicated to continuous learning for organizational success.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Software Development: Python, SQL, R, MATLAB, HTML, CSS, Bash, Git, Flask, Tensor Flow
- Visualization/Dashboarding: Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly, Tableau, Power BI (DAX), Qlik, SAS, Excel (VBA)
- Database/Cloud/Warehouse: PostgreSQL, Oracle SQL, MySQL, MS SQL Server, SSIS, SSRS, SSAS, AWS, MS Azure, Snowflake
- ML Modeling/Statistics: Predictive modeling, Recommendation system, A/B Testing, Aggregation, Time Series Analysis

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## Jr Machine Learning Engineer – Omdena, Houston, TX

2023 - Present

- Developed a FLASK-based web app for real estate price prediction, attracting over 1000 users within the first month, showcasing a 30% month-to-month increase in user engagement.
- Led a collaborative, end-to-end machine-learning initiative to investigate the crime-weather nexus in Houston, achieving a **75%** accuracy rate with the predictive model and enhancing accessibility through **Gradio app** integration.

## **Data Science Fellow –** Springboard, Houston, TX

2023 - 2023

- Completed an intensive 600 hours of data science training, illustrating a commitment to skill development and continuous learning.
- Executed two in-depth data science projects, one of which led to a **10% improvement in customer retention**, estimated to generate an additional **\$50,000 in annual revenue**. Applied data science techniques to identify cost-saving opportunities.

## **Sr Data Analyst –** Senor Enterprises Inc, Houston, TX

2019 - 2022

- Evaluated, developed, and maintained financial reports to communicate actual results effectively, and implemented more rigorous check and balance policies to avoid transaction mistakes.
- Utilized advanced data analysis skills to visualize, mine, and manipulated a 5-year database using Excel and Tableau, resulting in a **10% increase in branch performance** and revenue with an estimated **annual savings of \$400,000**.

# Technical Data Analyst - Robert Half Technologies, Fremont, CA

2018 - 2019

- Streamlined the diagnostic assessment process, reducing average examination time by 15% and increasing system uptime. This
  efficiency contributed to significant time and cost savings.
- Effectively managed project timelines, ensuring on-time completion and reducing downtime. This increased productivity, optimized ticketing system workflow, reduced response time to 20%, and enhanced fault documentation accuracy.

# **Data Analytics Researcher –** *Chalmers University of Technology*

2015 - 2017

- Conducted research on geodetic stations to enhance weather effects monitoring on signal propagation. Implemented data processing optimizations that **reduced computational resource usage by 15%**, resulting in a saving of 20% of processing time.
- Published research findings in a detailed report, enhancing the university's reputation and attracting additional research funding for
  related projects. This research also led to a 10% improvement in signal propagation monitoring accuracy and quality of collected data.

### **Market Data Analyst** – *ZTE Corporations*

2013 - 2014

- Analyzed and evaluated 3G/4G market data, resulting in a 15% increase in market share and a \$2 million boost in revenue. This
  analysis directly contributed to ZTE Corporation's financial growth.
- Streamlined and data collection process, reducing the time required by 20% allowing for more timely insights and faster decision making. Additionally, generated actionable insights that improved market understanding by 20% enabling more informed decisions.

#### **SELECTED PROJECTS**

- Developed a web app using FLASK and machine learning to predict real estate prices.
- Understanding crime and weather relationships in Houston, Texas by using machine learning, an end-to-end project.
- Build a Human Resource Management System using Oracle SQL Server, SQL querying, and report building.
- H&M fashion recommendation system uses a large dataset incorporating images to provide personalized product suggestions.
- NLP-based text classification and sentiment analysis of COVID-19 tweets using statistical tools and achieved 64% accuracy.
- New York City Airbnb price prediction using machine learning achieved R-squared = 57%, MSE = 0.19, and MAE = 0.14.

## **EDUCATION**

- MS Computer Science (Data Analytics, Machine learning) Sofia University, Palo Alto, CA
- BS Engineering (Computer Science, Telecommunications) FAST-National University, International